<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-12T19:41:40+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Skanda Vivek</title><subtitle>A flexible Jekyll theme for your blog or site with a minimalist aesthetic.</subtitle><author><name>Skanda Vivek</name></author><entry><title type="html">Rich Dad/Poor Dad</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/rich-poor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rich Dad/Poor Dad" /><published>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/rich-poor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/rich-poor/">&lt;p&gt;I was pleasantly surprised this financial best seller emphasizes the mindset of creating value for the life you want,
rather than running after money. Kiyosaki’s birth father was an intellectual man, but apparently lost his money because of poor financial
decisions. The rich dad was Kiyosaki’s friend’s dad, who taught him lessons in financial literacy and financial freedom, through allowing Kiyosaki
to follow in his footsteps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images2/richpoor.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images2/richpoor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover by Skanda Vivek&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the book, Kiyosaki illustrates the financial lessons he learned by working for his friend’s father. One such lesson is that the rich don’t work for money.
To me this statement makes sense as Kiyosaki explains it - the middle class is caught in a never ending trap of making stable but low wages. As a result,
many hardworking folks have to work extremely hard to make ends meet, sometimes working multiple jobs. This in combination with a lack of accounting for
financial conditions and a tendency to waste money on non-essential items leads to a cycle of wealth loss and poverty. However, one thing he says about “rich”
people particularly stands out. It’s not about getting rich quickly through some scheme or some clever way no one has ever thought of. And it doesn’t even
have anything to do with money. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Be an observer, not a reactor to your emotions. Most people do not know that it is their emotions that are doing the thinking. Your emotions are
your emotions, but you have got to do the thinking.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is a profound statement, that does not have to do only with making money. But also leading a rich, fulfilling life not necessarily associated
with a dollar amount. Mastering the mind is a crucial step it seems, to being financially succesful. If you read my &lt;a href=&quot;https://skandavivek.com/blog/gandhi/&quot;&gt;post on Gandhi&lt;/a&gt;, you will see that the lessons
he writes about (“To attain [perfection], one has to become absolutely passion-free in thought, speech and action; to rise above the opposing currents of love and hatred, attachment and repulsion”)
resonates with Kiyosaki’s ideas too. If you had told me 2 years ago that Gandhi’s book and a financial best seller
have the same underlying theme, I would have never believed you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next lesson talks about learning the tools of financial literacy: namely assets vs liabilities. Kiyosaki simply states: the rich buy assets, the poor have expenses,
and the middle class buys liabilities that they think are assets. He treats a house that one lives in as a liability, and a bigger house as a bigger liability. That
does not mean that he doesn’t like real estate though, quite the opposite - he made his initial fortune and quit his day job because of a succesful real estate side
business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic tools for financial literacy are understanding assets and liabilities. And understanding how the income made and expenses incurred result in cash flows into and
from assets and liabilities The income earned by the middle class flows into liabilities, and expenses. Whereas the rich generate income from assets. A quite remarkable
example is the fast food chain McDonalds. The CEO of McDonalds, Ray Kroc, famously asked students what business he was in. They laughed and said of course hamburgers.
But he said that McDonalds was in fact in the real estate business, and not the hamburger business. McDonalds is one of the world’s largest real estate companies and
has a unique arrangement with it’s franchises to whom it leases its land at a marked up price. Kiyosaki illustrates that one should know the difference between
one’s business and one’s profession. Business translates into multiple complex life decisions, whereas one’s profession is only a piece of the entire puzzle. Kiyosaki
of course talks about how to shield from taxes by forming the right sort of company. In regards to working in a job, Kiyosaki says that you should work to learn, rather than working to earn money. Look down the road at skills you wish to acquire, before chosing a profession and potentially getting
trapped in the rat race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final section of his book is titled “Teach and you shall receive.” This particularly resonates with me, as I like teaching in various formats. And recently with the online
education explosion, I have much truth to this statement - from students who enjoy my online resources to those who read my blogs and research articles and for lifelong
collaborations. Youtuber David Perrel (according to another youtuber Ali Abdaal) makes a wonderful statement about online writing. He says think about if you live in a small
village and don’t go out too much - your contacts, interactions, and ideas are limited to those from within the village. But what if you take a trip every week to a far away place?
You might meet all sorts of people with all sorts of ideas, have serendipitous connections and broaden your mind. So go forth and put your work out there.
You might never know all the possible value for your approach, and you might be useful. It’s not possible to imagine all the future possibilities and opportunities
that could result from just putting your work out there. I say this from first hand experience. Multiple times. Even though I’m not super popular. If I can do it, so can you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on a suggestion by the incredible Youtuber &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AjoxkxM_I5g&quot;&gt;Ali Abdaaal&lt;/a&gt;, I’m going to summarize 3 key points I learnt from this book as well as 3 quotes that stood out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-takeaways&quot;&gt;3 Takeaways:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The rich get richer because their assets generate more than enough income to cover expenses. The middle class struggles because their primary income is through salary. As salaries rise, so do taxes. And middle class income is spent towards liabilities. Assets are dissolved to help pay for uncovered expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The McDonalds example teaches that sometimes one’s business is different from one’s profession. Recently I’ve come across Youtube study channels - the person makes money by sharing their screen and surroundings while they are studying, and viewers watch their videos and probably study alongside. These people are literally making assets out of just their immediate surroundings and making money off it, while their profession is what they are studying for (e.g. medical school).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t work for money - rather, work to learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-quotes&quot;&gt;3 Quotes:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Be an observer, not a reactor to your emotions. Most people do not know that it is their emotions that are doing the thinking. Your emotions are
your emotions, but you have got to do the thinking.””&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Work to learn - don’t work for money”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Each dollar in my asset column was a great employee, working hard to make more employees and buy the boss a new Porsche.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;caveats&quot;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serendipitously, I found an &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/swlh/were-not-getting-financially-smarter-by-reading-rich-dad-poor-dad-728c6c62fc4a&quot;&gt;article by Tim Denning&lt;/a&gt;
as I finished up this article, on the very same book! He points out how Kiyosaki does not exactly give the best financial advice these days. So keep this in mind that this post is not
a thumbs up for all of Kiyosaki’s advice. And this post is not financial advice. It represents my thoughts on a financial best seller, and my learnings from it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Skanda Vivek</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html">I was pleasantly surprised this financial best seller emphasizes the mindset of creating value for the life you want, rather than running after money. Kiyosaki’s birth father was an intellectual man, but apparently lost his money because of poor financial decisions. The rich dad was Kiyosaki’s friend’s dad, who taught him lessons in financial literacy and financial freedom, through allowing Kiyosaki to follow in his footsteps.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons Learned: The Story Of My Experiments With Truth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/gandhi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons Learned: The Story Of My Experiments With Truth" /><published>2021-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/gandhi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/gandhi/">&lt;p&gt;Reading Gandhi’s autobiography last year opened up my eyes to the importance of mental discipline and training, which is not often as discussed as physical training. But I would argue that mental training is as important (if not more) than physical training. The difference is that when you train your body, you see improvements when you look at yourself in the mirror. This positive feedback gives you motivation to continue exercising as part of a weekly regimen. In most cases, the mirror is a true physical reflection of your physical self. However, there is no such reflection of an improving mental prowess. Nevertheless, it is extremely important to train the mind. Think about your daily life - how many times do you need to do heavy physical labor like farm work? As compared to how much time do you spend using your brain to solve complex problems - sitting at your computer, or discussing with co-workers, or teaching someone else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images2/gandhi.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images2/gandhi.png&quot; alt=&quot;Portrait of Gandhi by Indrajit Das&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi summarizes his life’s work as a never ending search for truth. In the final farewell chapter, he summarizes what he has learnt through years of perseverence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To attain [perfection], one has to become absolutely passion-free in thought, speech and action; to rise above the opposing currents of love and hatred, attachment and repulsion”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gandhi-in-south-africa&quot;&gt;Gandhi in South Africa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reading this book I had some conception that Gandhi spent sometime in South Africa. However, I was unaware how vital his time in South Africa was, for his contribution to India. It was in South Africa that he formed his most valuable ideas, including the concept of Satyagraha. Gandhi spent more than two decades from 1893-1914 in South Africa, in order to practice law and represent Indians in cases. Considering he went there when he was only 23, shows the impact South Africa had when he was in his formative years. While he went there for a specific case, in order to represent an Indian merchant, he immediately encountered intense racism in South Africa, directed towards Indians. He spent much time organizing peaceful protests, and fighting injustice through the legal system. As a lawyer, Gandhi was uniquely poised simultaneously as a man of knowledge, reputation, and respect for existing judicial systems, while at the same time his quest for the truth and justice made him the champion of underrepresented and persecuted Indians living in South Africa. For a long time, Gandhi was convinced that these racial injustices were limited to South Africa, and that the British rule was good in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi’s good deeds in South Africa made him famous in India. In 1896, Gandhi visited India to visit his family, and also to educate the people in the Indian National Congress about the plight of Indians in South Africa. It was then that he started being aware of the defects in the British rule. In one particular incident, for Queen Victoria’s diamond jubilee event he decided to join along in the reciting of the British national anthem. A verse in particular stood out for Gandhi, as he describes in his chapter “Two Passions:”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“O Lord our God arise,
Scatter her enemies
And make them fall;
Confound their politics,
Frustrate their knavish tricks,
On Thee our hopes we fix,
God, save us all!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marked the beginning of his questioning of the British rule in India, and eventual struggle for India’s freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-choose&quot;&gt;How to choose?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s world we are faced with so many choices. For me personally, it is often hard to make a choice. There’s so many options of what research to prioritize, which blogging platform to use, whether to invest time in starting a newsletter, and even smaller decisions of what font size to use. I recognize this as a specific aspect that I need to train towards - efficient decision making. But I’m particularly inspired by an incident that showed Gandhi’s thought process during decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he had gone back to India in 1896, he started noticing the strain of daily Indian life due to the British rule. When he was speaking with members from the Indian National Congress about supporting the cause for Indians in South Africa, he angered some members, in particular one Pestonji Padshah. He said to Gandhi: ‘It is impossible to help you. Is there a lack of work in our own country? Let us win self-government here and we shall automatically help our countrymen there.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi could definitely understand this point of view and was faced by the important decision: give up work in South Africa and fight for India’s freedom, or go back to South Africa to complete the work to improve the conditions of Indians there? In making a choice, Gandhi went to the Bhagvad Gita, an Indian epic detailing the ambivalence of the great Indian warrior Arjuna during the Mahabharatha war, in fighting for the truth, but requiring to make great sacrifices and decisions in the process. Paraphrasing a key paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This is better that one do,
His own task as he may, even though he fail,
Than take tasks not his own, though they seem good,
To die performing duty is no ill:
But who seeks other roads shall wander still.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand this beautiful paragraph as echoing multiple content creators who say “find your niche” -  whether on Medium or Youtube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-larger-picture&quot;&gt;The larger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi’s case study shows how having a self-critical mindset with the intent of finding truth in everyday life can lead to the great outcomes, even the freedom of a country. I must point out the caveat that there are many flaws to Gandhi as a person, and questions on whether Gandhi’s contributions were necessary for Indian freedom. Nevertheless, Gandhi is one of the most famous (if not the most famous) Indians, and his philosophies of non-violence and the incessant search for truth have impacted the entire world. That in of itself is testament to his beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, until Gandhi ultimately came to India in his mid 40’s he did not seriously consider freedom of Indian under the British rule as a motivating factor. He was just extremely aware of the injustices around him, and did his best to fix them. This mental attitude alone led him to solve societies big problems of the time. In fact, when he returned to India in 1900, with the intent to settle down in Mumbai and practice at the bar, he was immediately summoned back to South Africa to meet the Prime Minister of U.K., Mr. Chamberlain. Throughout his life, Gandhi accepted calls from people who needed his support, and also ultimately when his whole country needed him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a physicist, I draw parallels with the emergence of large scale macroscopic properties from microscopic interactions. A crystal is composed of individual atoms that don’t know how to place themselves, yet a beautiful structure emerges. How is this possible? This is due to the microscopic interactions between individual molecules, leading to emergent patterns. The same goes for my professional activities - I strive to make the best choice in the moment, without explicitly knowing what results these decisions might make in the larger picture. But with the hope that decades later, a story that made a difference will emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Skanda Vivek</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html">Reading Gandhi’s autobiography last year opened up my eyes to the importance of mental discipline and training, which is not often as discussed as physical training. But I would argue that mental training is as important (if not more) than physical training. The difference is that when you train your body, you see improvements when you look at yourself in the mirror. This positive feedback gives you motivation to continue exercising as part of a weekly regimen. In most cases, the mirror is a true physical reflection of your physical self. However, there is no such reflection of an improving mental prowess. Nevertheless, it is extremely important to train the mind. Think about your daily life - how many times do you need to do heavy physical labor like farm work? As compared to how much time do you spend using your brain to solve complex problems - sitting at your computer, or discussing with co-workers, or teaching someone else?</summary></entry></feed>